<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An assembly lecture, or, A sermon held forth at a conventicle upon this text, Saint's practice, chapter I, verse I : it is lawful for the saints to cheat the wicked / by a maintainer of the saint's priviledge and liberty of conscience.</title>
            <author>Maintainer of the saint's priviledge and liberty of conscience.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26047</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36640</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15747102</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15747102</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104619</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26047)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104619)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1164:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An assembly lecture, or, A sermon held forth at a conventicle upon this text, Saint's practice, chapter I, verse I : it is lawful for the saints to cheat the wicked / by a maintainer of the saint's priviledge and liberty of conscience.</title>
                  <author>Maintainer of the saint's priviledge and liberty of conscience.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104619:1"/>
            <p>AN Aſſembly Lecture OR A SERMON, Held forth at a CONVENTICLE. UPON THIS TEXT, Saint's Practice, <hi>Chapter,</hi> 1. <hi>Verſe</hi> 1. <hi>It is Lawful for the Saints to Cheat the Wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a <hi>Maintainer,</hi> of the Saint's Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and Liberty of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veritas, acerba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year. 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104619:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104619:2"/>
            <head>It is lawful for the Saints to Cheat the VVicked.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Saints are Innumerable, ſo their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges are Infinite: The Stars of the Skie may be told; in counting the Sands of the Sea, or the Duſt of the Field, we may come to one that is Laſt; the Ocean has its Bounds, but the pretended Saints Priviledges are beyond Meaſure, they are Boundleſs. There is no State, no Power, no Law, can Rule them, but like the Wind which Blows where it liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, they are freed from all Control, and ſubject to nothing but the Directory of their own Will and Appetite.</p>
            <p>This is the Compaſs by which they Steer, this is the Hand which ſhews the Time, let the Sun of Truth ſay what it will. The Infalibility of the <hi>Pope</hi> is much talked of, the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the <hi>Grand Sultan</hi> is very High and Imperious, but the Saints Priviledge is Elevated above them all; and was it lawful to ſay, that it always went aſtray, yet may we be aſſured, it never Errs, 'tis never out o'th' way.</p>
            <p>The Saints Priviledge cannot be perfectly Defined, for there is nothing more General, its Eſſence cannot be known: Only this we can ſay, that the Saints Priviledg, is the Saints Priviledge.</p>
            <p>But that you may have ſome Hints of this Metaphyſical ſuperſtitious accident, I will deſcribe it (although imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly) yet as plainly as its Nature will afford.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104619:3"/>
            <p>Some derive the word Priviledge from <hi>Lex &amp; Privata,</hi> and define it to be <hi>Lex Privata homini irrogata;</hi> a Private Law given to a Man. But conſidering it is the Saints Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge (that ſingular Priviledge) we are to handle, as moſt agreeable and ſuiting to the Saint, I ſhall derive the word from <hi>Lex &amp; Privatio,</hi> and ſo define it to be <hi>Legis Privatio;</hi> a Privation, and taking away of the Law, for it is therefore called Priviledge, becauſe it Exempts them from the Power of the Law, and divides them from the common Condition of Mankind.</p>
            <p>And here I am prevented of parting and diſtributing this general thing, Priviledge, into the ſeveral ſorts; for I am fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the Mouth of Diviſion before I was aware, I am fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len amongſt the Saints, and upon their Priviledge, which is ſo proper to them; that as that Diſtinguiſhes them from all the People of the World, ſo they diſtinguiſh that from all other ſorts of Priviledges, and both of them together, Cut, Divide, and Mangle the whole Univerſe into Parties, Sects, and Factions.</p>
            <p>This Saintly Priviledge belongs to thoſe Men who are commonly called <hi>Seperatiſts, Phanaticks,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe are thoſe <hi>Meduſa</hi>'s Heads, on which grow many Snakes, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, that are full of Venom, and yet have lovely Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Out-ſides, ſuch as would Deceive <hi>Eve</hi> again, if ſhe Lived in <hi>Paradiſe;</hi> and do beguile her Progeny at this day, devouring Widdows Houſes, even with their long Prayers, and by Groans and Whinings, delude the Multitude, as <hi>Mahomet</hi> did with Fits. A form of Godlineſs they have, but their Hearts are full of Impieties, their Minds full of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Rebellion, their Hands full of Rapine, Blood, Murthers and Regicides; witneſs the Tragedy of the late Times.</p>
            <p>But not to Deſcribe them only by the Habits of their Minds, whereſoever you ſee a man exalted in a Meeting-Houſe, doing penance in the ſurface of a White Cap, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viron'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104619:3"/>with an Aſſembly-Cloak, or a Frize Coat, which helps in ſtead of a <hi>Hum,</hi> or a <hi>Ha,</hi> to ſpend time, by pulling forwards the <hi>Coat,</hi> firſt on one Shoulder, then on the other, whilſt the more unwilling Matter, which ſticks below, is pull'd up, and brought to Utterance: Whereſoever you ſee one thus Clad, Whining and Groaning as if he Laboured for Life; the poſture of his Eyes in one Extream or other, either turning up the Whites to Amaze and Affright the Spectators, or ſhutting of them cloſe, as aſhamed of himſelf, the Place and Company. This is one of thoſe Wolves in Sheeps Cloathing: This is the Sounding Braſs and Tinkling Cymbal: This is one of the Adders which Grows on the Head I mentioned before; and the Subject to which the Saints Priviledge doth appertain.</p>
            <p>You may meet theſe Serpents Crawling up and down in other Shapes, differing from the former, ſome with Beads in their Hands, others with no Superſtitious Relicks I'le aſſure you; no, not ſo much as a Hatband on their Hats, or a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond on the lower Covering of the outward Man; a Fry whoſe <hi>Lenten</hi> Faces ſhew they were Spawned of Shotten Herrings, and meet together only to compare Uncouth Looks. There are many more, which I forbear to Enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, reſerving them for another place, and ſo I paſs from the Unclean Cage where this Bird (the Saints Priviledge) Rouſts, and come to its Object, about which it is Imployed, and the end for which it is uſed, as alſo the Principles from which it moves.</p>
            <p>The chief Uſe of this Priviledge is, to compaſs and bring about the Deſigns of the Saint: His Deſigns are twofold, namely, Profit and Honour; Avarice prompts him to Inrich himſelf, and Pride puts him upon ſeeking Reputation in the World; he loves to be Admired, and Eſteemed amongſt the Brethren, as a precious Heavenly minded man; but in the mean time he Aims at Worldly Intereſt, and the Obtaining ſome Benefit to himſelf: And to accompliſh this, what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104619:4"/>Courſe can he take then Satan did when he firſt tempted Mankind, that is Allure them with the diſcerning Knowledg of Good and Evil; and here he muſt Teach them what is Good, and what is Evil: He is Good, and therefore muſt be followed; others are Evil, and therefore muſt be avoided, and when he has perſwaded the ſilly Multitude into this Belief, then he is likely to have a fruitful Harveſt, and his Barns fill'd with a plentiful Crop, and his Projects will go on ſucceſsfully; but in this Carreer he will meet with many Obſtructions; many Laws will oppoſe him, Religion will hinder him, the Settled Government of moſt States and Kingdoms will Thwart him; wherefore to clear the way, and overthrow Laws, Religion and Kingdoms, he muſt Fly to the Saints Priviledg, which being Skilfully managed, will procure his Hearts deſire.</p>
            <p>Before the Apparition of this Harpy, was the Time Men call the Golden Age; Religion was then Imbraced for its own ſake, not to cover other Deſigns; Men ſtrove to be Religious indeed, rather then to be thought ſo: The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Concern of all was to ſerve Heaven, and love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Such! ſuch, was the Uniformity of that Age, Peace and Plenty kiſſed each other, and Univerſal Obedience to the Laws, made the Governours happy, and the Subjects bleſſed. But when this Saints Priviledg ſtarted up, Ten Thouſand Miſchiefs did accompany it, Pride, Envie, Strife, Covetuouſneſs, and innumerable other Sins were its Life-Guard; thence followed Faction, Schiſm, Treaſon, Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, Murther of Princes, Deſtruction of Religion, Laws, States, and Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Lucijers</hi> ambition cauſed him to attempt the Dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of God Almighty, ſo this Saints Priviledg makes them ſet their Mouths againſt Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, whilſt Meekneſs, Humility, Religion, and true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Piety perſwade them otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Thus have we, ſo briefly as we could, Repreſented to you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104619:4"/>the Saints Priviledg, whereof we intend to ſpeak; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this Priviledg is manifold, as you have already heard, yet at this time we will only take a Branch of it, which is that contained in the Text, namely,</p>
            <q>It is lawful for the Saints to Cheat the Wicked.</q>
            <p>In which words, obſerve with me Four Things: Firſt the Act, namely, <hi>To Cheat.</hi> Secondly, The Actors, which are <hi>The Saints.</hi> Thirdly, The Patient, or Object of this Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely, <hi>The Wicked.</hi> And Fourthly, The Quality of the Act, that is, <hi>Lawful: It is lawful for the Saints to Cheat the Wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt of the Act, <hi>To Cheat:</hi> Cheat is a word of a large Signification, it comprehends all Sin, and extends to all Vitious Actions; there are many words Equivalent to this, and are uſed in the ſame ſenſe, as to Defraud, Cozen, Deceive, Delude, Over-reach, Beguile, Betray, and the like; and of Affinity with theſe, are Deceits, Covin, Fraud, Deluſion, Treachery, Impoſture, Hypocriſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And from hence Knaves, Impoſtors, Traytors, Deceivers, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, Diſſemblers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> receive Denomination; and all theſe agree with our Saint in the Text.</p>
            <p>Cheating is the chief Inſtrument of the Devil, and the Engin by which he brings about his greateſt Works, by this he brought Deſtruction upon Mankind, beguiling our firſt Parents with his Inſinuating Flatteries, ſubtilly taking upon him the form of a Glittering Serpent; firſt catching the Eye, our Senſes, that thereby he might have Entrance, to lay hold upon our ſouls.</p>
            <p>Oh! how prevalent are ſubtle Flatteries, eſpecially thoſe which come with ſuch ſpecious pretences, as this Serpents did: <hi>Yea, hath God ſaid, ye ſhall not Eat of every Tree of the Garden?</hi> Doth he ſay that if you do, ye ſhall ſurely die? I tell you, nay, ye ſhall not die, <hi>For God doth know that in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104619:5"/>the day ye Eat thereof, then your Eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as Gods, knowing Good and Evil.</hi> I ſay, how preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and irreſiſtable are ſuch plauſible Temptations! other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, methinks the Commands of the great Creator, ſo new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Impoſed, immediately after the Creation, might have Deterred the Creature from ſin; the fear of Death, one would think, might have reſtrained the Appetite, let the Object have been never ſo deſirable; ſurely the poſture of the Serpents Turning and Twining, ſeeming to go one way and another, but in truth goes neither, might have made them ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect him; No, <hi>Knowledge, and to be as Gods,,</hi> are ſuch Temptations, that Innocency it ſelf cannot reſiſt them.</p>
            <p>Wherefore our Saint taking pattern from the great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, forms all his Impoſtures and Deluſions, in the ſame Mold that Satan did his, and ſets before the People the Temptations of Knowledge, Religion, the ſpirit of Light, to be as Gods, Liberty, Freedom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> telling them that if they follow him, and do as he directs, their Eyes ſhall be opened, and they ſhall know themſelves to be the only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious choſen people of God, freed from the ſpots and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the World, freed from the powers of the Earth, and from the Obligation of Laws, either of the Church or State, whilſt in the mean time, they make Room for Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Implicitly teach their Followers to diſobey the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and his Vice-gerents.</p>
            <p>For which purpoſe there muſt be (and is already pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed) a new Book of <hi>Ethicks,</hi> to teach the VVorld to break Laws with a good Conſcience; wherein it is Aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that penal Laws may be broken, and that by the Intent of the Law-Maker, who impoſes a Mulct or penalty upon the Offender, and thereby commutes the Obedience for the Penalty. Excellent Doctrine! and I doubt not but it will be well Improved; better cannot be Expected from a Tavern, Ale-houſe, or Meeting-houſe, where penal Laws are daily broken: But ſurely though the Law be ſo in his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104619:5"/>Conſcience, who is a notorious Offender, and muſt uſe Clouts to wrap up the Sores of his Conſcience; yet other men obey the Law, and are ſubject to every Ordinance of Man for Conſcience-ſake, and do not wilfully offend that they might pay the Penalty, but think the Law is Obligato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Conſcience, and the Penalty is added by way of Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation, to Deter men from the Offence: For if the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Law-giver was not to have ſincere Obedience, his Laws would be rather Tricks to get Money, then In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for the better Ordering and Governing So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties.</p>
            <p>And if Obedience be Due in this manner to Laws (as without all doubt it is) and the Scripture injoyns us to be ſubject to them: How dare we obſtinately and reſolutely Diſobey them? How dare we meet in Conventicles, which is forbidden by the Law, being found by ſad Experience dangerous to the State, and the occaſion of Strife and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, thoſe deſtructives of Humane Society? How dare we? Why, I muſt appeal to our Saint in the Text, who has an Anſwer ready prepared for him by his great Maſter; who, as I have already ſhewed you: Preached, <hi>Yea, hath God ſaid, ye ſhall not eat,</hi> &amp;c. So our Saint, yea, doth the Law ſay we ſhall not meet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I tell you, that you may; we have a Priviledge in Conſcience, to Tranſgreſs and Break what Laws we pleaſe: <hi>It is lawful for the Saints,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here I might Expoſe our Saint to ſhame enough, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering his Nakedneſs, and pulling off that Vizard with which he doth deceive the World; but when I conſider that 'tis impoſſible to Enumerate half his Cheats, and they are ſo frequently Practiſed that every one meets with them, I purpoſely forbear a particular Account, referring you to the Hiſtory of the late Times, where they ſwarm.</p>
            <p>And inſtead of a Catalogue, I preſent you with a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, which like <hi>Phaeton</hi>'s, ſets the World on Fire. This Chariot is the Saints Cheat I now ſpeak of, the Wheels are the Ignorance of the People, and the Admiration they have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104619:6"/>of him: The Horſes that draw this Chariot, are his Pride and Covetuouſneſs: Our Saint is the Driver, and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle is his Whip.</p>
            <p>I have ſpoken of the Chariot already, which has a Stage almoſt in every Town of all Countries, and Travels up and down the World, being carried to every thing; by the Horſes, Pride and Covetouſneſs: I will now ſay ſomewhat of the Wheels, Ignorance is a good Wheel, on this the Chariot runs ſwiftly; where the People are Learned, the Chariot moves ſlowly, Letters are like Clogs, and good Rudiments are ſuch a Burthen, that it cannot ſtir; where men are well Educated in the Prinicples of Religion, our Saints Cheat can hardly paſs, but amongſt the Ignorant it runs poſt. And this Wheell has a good Fellow, namely, the Admiration which the People have for our Saint, for when he has once Inſinuated himſelf into them, ſo that they have a good Opinion of him and Admire him, then the Chariot gets ground, and flies merrily; then all he ſays is Goſpel, and nay, more Authentick then the Goſpel; for <hi>Calvin</hi> was ſo Admired by a— (you may know him by his Speech) that he profeſſed if St. <hi>Paul</hi> were Alive, and to Preach the ſame hour that <hi>Calvin</hi> did, he would leave St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and go to hear <hi>Calvin:</hi> You may believe him, for <hi>Calvins</hi> Writings are followed and preferred before St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> Oh brave Wheel! well Greaſed! and Excellently well fitted to the Chariot!</p>
            <p>Of the Horſes, Pride or Covetuouſneſs, I cannot tell which Excels. Pride has moſt Mettle, but Covetuouſneſs is the ſureſt Drawer. To be Applauded for Excellent parts, for a Singular man, for a Gifted man, for a Leading man; to be called <hi>Rabbi,</hi> to be eſteemed a ſure Guid of Souls, a true ſetter of Conſcience, to be Wiſer then thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him; To have Silence made at a Conventicle, and be ſet above the reſt by Head and Shoulders; to have Liberty to Speak what he pleaſes, and that more to the Nodifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104619:6"/>then edification, of the beholders, for they Edifie little, but Nod much; I ſay theſe preheminences puff up, and ſomtimes move the chariot briskly, a little pride many times induces a great cheat, yet this Horſe is often jaded; for although our Saints ambition makes him aſpire above Heaven it ſelf, yet frequently have I known, when cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſs draws one way, and pride another, covetu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſneſs has got the better, and went away with the Chariot: To be head of an Aſſembly, ſole Teacher, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer, not ſubject to Law or Magiſtrate, is very accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but a Good Living, a Fat Benefice, has made our Saint leave them all, and be Subordinate to Legal Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Nay, this Horſe has been ſo ſtrong, that it hath drawn the Chariot to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> to help our Saint in, even by one of his Contracts.</p>
            <p>Covetuouſneſs hath made him Prey upon the Brethren themſelves, he has warmed their Zeal ſo hot, by preſſing the Duty upon them, of Raiſing Money to Build a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticling Houſe, that they have Contributed, and given him Money enough to Build one; and when he has Built it, he has made Uſe of the Houſe for himſelf, and turned the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren out; telling them the Houſe was not ſo Convenient as he thought it would have been, and that he knew of another Place, much more convenient, for the Service; and hath wrought upon them ſo, that they have made a new Collection, and Built another Houſe: And thus our Saint has ſerved them Two or Three times, and Chouſed them of Two or Three Houſes one after another.</p>
            <p>Ah! This Horſe Covetuouſneſs, is an unruly Beaſt, he draws our Saint to all manner of Viecs, to Lying, Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, Falſhhood in Dealing, nay, even to the ſins of the Fleſh; many, yea, many a time hath he drawn our Saint to his Neighbour's Wife, and there ſo Kicked and Frisked, that he hath thrown our Saint upon her; Ah! threw him even upon her.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:104619:7"/>
            <p>Truly, this Horſe is ſo Ungoverned, that no man can Live in quiet near our Saint, he Breaks down his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Fences, eats up his Graſs, and his Corn, and is ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten taken <hi>Damage Fefant,</hi> that was he not a ſerviceable Horſe, and very profitable to our Saint, he would not keep him.</p>
            <p>But ſo long as he Draws the Chariot well, our Saint will not part with him, his Neighbour muſt endure him.</p>
            <p>One Faculty this Horſe has, which makes our Saint high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prize him, he is an excellent ſtretcher of Conſcience, no Bars and Tenter hooks can ſtretch Cloth half ſo well; take him in a Morning when he is Freſh, and put him to our Saints conſcience, he will draw it ſo wide, that 'twill ſwallow any thing.</p>
            <p>Having given you an Account of the Horſes; in the next place, we come to handle the Whip: And conſidering the Horſes appear to be ſo good, ſo Mettleſom, and ſuch ſure Drawers, one would think our Saint needed no Whip; Yet a Whip is very needful, and that will appear to you in theſe particulars: I do not intend to ſpeak any thing in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement of the Horſes; for I agree there cannot be Two more ſerviceable Horſes in the World, and were they in an Ordinary mans ſervice, without all doubt a Whip would be altogether unneceſſary. But you muſt underſtand, our Saint is a very hard Rider, he Drives furiouſly, I never met him in my life but that he was above three quarters ſpeed, upon common occaſions he Rides poſt, and about Matters more then ordinary, he Rides as <hi>Jockies</hi> ride Races; in a Furlong and a Half he leaves the man, that Rides for the Midwife above a Furlong behind him. Now for ſuch a Hot-ſpur as this, you will agree that a Whip is requiſite; But what Whip? Not any Whip, not a common Whip, it muſt be a Whip of many cords, that hath many Laſhes, it muſt be a Whip ſuitable to our Saints deſigns, and therefore ſurely a Whip of his own making is beſt, and that's a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104619:7"/>For this has many Cords, many Laſhes, it hath many Rich, and they ſerve as ſo many Cords for the Horſe <hi>Covetuouſneſs;</hi> It hath many Admirers of our Saint, and they ſerve as ſo many Laſhes for the other Horſe <hi>Pride:</hi> Theſe Motives are the Spurs that prick on the Palfreys which hurry away the Chariot. Our Saint is never ſo Rampant as at a Conventicle; there his Pride Snorts and Prances, ſpurns at Government, condemning and contemning all thoſe that are not of his Way, and ſcornfully pitying all thoſe poor loſt Creatures that Gainſay a Meeting-Houſe. Ah poor ſouls! they live in ſin, there is no hopes of them, they know not Good from Evil, they are ſtupified, and have no ſenſe of the Joy, and Refreſhments, that we have at our Meetings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time Covetuouſneſs claps his Tail betwixt his Legs, lays his Ears cloſe to his Head, and Leers at the Rich and Wealthy Brethren! he pulls the Chariot hard, towards the Siſters Silver and Gold Bodkins, and with ſuch Concupiſence, that ſometimes he gets Bodkin, Siſter and all.</p>
            <p>'Tis very fit I ſhould now tell you how our Saint handles his Whip, and in doing this, I muſt ſhew you the place, where Policy hath Taught our Saint to put the Whip: That Ale-houſe, that Inn, that Tavern, is beſt Scituated, and moſt Dexterouſly contrived that hath a Thorough-fair (as 'tis called) in it, for by that convenience Cuſtome is gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſo our Saint, that hath all the Tricks of a Tavern, or Tipling-houſe, hath likewiſe this, and places his Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle where there may be a Common Way or Paſſage tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row it, in hopes thereby to Catch ſome ſilly Gudgeon or other, that comes near his Not, ſo Mountebanks gain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; And he well knows that many Perſons fall into the Looſe Sport of Pidgeon-Holes, meerly upon the occaſion of paſſing by them: Therefore with wonted Craft doth our Saint order his Conventicle.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104619:8"/>
            <p>It follows, that I accoſt the Driver, but he looks ſo <hi>Jehu</hi>-like, that I dare not Meddle with him, <hi>qua Driver.</hi> I ſhall meet with him in the Text, being the ſecond Thing I deſired you to obſerve therein: <hi>It is lawful for the Saints to Cheat the Wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have at large Treated of the Act contained in the Text, namely, <hi>The Cheat:</hi> I am now come to the <hi>Actors,</hi> and thoſe you ſee are Saints; what kind of Saints, partly appears by that has been ſaid, and ſhall be ſhewed here more fully.</p>
            <p>Some divide Mankind into two ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> The Godly, and the Ungodly: In truth and reality, our Saint muſt be Ranked under the latter Head, for ('tis too plain) his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhew him to be one of that Party. But he has a Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (the Priviledge I ſpake of before) to be accounted and reckoned amongſt the Godly; and as one of that Form we muſt take him here, in reſpect of his Priviledge, to be Reputed ſo, but not in reſpect of his Practices, for they ſhew him to be quite another thing. I promiſed you to ſub-divide thoſe general Heads of <hi>Separatiſt, Phanatick,</hi> &amp;c. and preſent you with the ſeveral ſorts and fryes, that are contained under them; but ſeeing the Diſtinctions would be Infinite (ſo much have they been ever given to Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) I ſhould confound you with ſub-diviſions, and new names: For every Sect takes up a new Name, with the old Villanies, they change the Name, but retain the Sin: As thoſe which were called <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, are now called <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and the like in a hundred Inſtances. Therefore I purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſs by the particulars, and hope our Saint will not Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with me for it. But you may know them by theſe Marks. Their Words and their Works never agree. They are Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niated of themſelves, and condemn all others. A Lye in a Brothers Mouth, is truer, then Truth it ſelf in another mans. They ſuſpect and conclude all men to be Wicked, but themſelves. They begin all their Miſchiefs, in the Name of the Lord, when they Act the greateſt Wickedneſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104619:8"/>in the World; they will bear down all, that it is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt piece of Piety, and Religion in the World. That which is unjuſt in another mans caſe, is moſt juſt in theirs. They will believe none but the confiding men of their own Party. By theſe Marks and many more like them, you may know the <hi>Saint</hi> meant in the Text. In a word, the World is his <hi>Stage,</hi> and he is to Act the Devils part, a part that has been Acting ever ſince the World began, and will not be Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, until the Worlds end.</p>
            <p>From the Actor or Agent, I turn to the Patient, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are to be <hi>Cheated,</hi> and thoſe are the Wicked: The Wicked! But who are they? In ſhort, they are all thoſe that do oppoſe the <hi>Saints.</hi> Oppoſe them! In what? In any thing. For if that which doth agree with the <hi>Saints</hi> is Righteous, then that which doth diſagree with the <hi>Saints</hi> is Unrighteous; hence it proceeds that our <hi>Saint</hi> doth and may Rail againſt Government, againſt the Laws, againſt Princes, againſt Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Rulers, for theſe Oppoſe the <hi>Saint,</hi> and therefore are wicked, yea, very wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and may be Cheated. But the Breakers of penal Laws, as the <hi>Vintners</hi> that ſell VVine above the Rates; the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants who ſteal Cuſtoms; they that draw Ale without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe; thoſe that Play at forbidden Games; they that keep Bawdy Houſes, and Conventicles in them: Theſe are not the VVicked intended in the Text, no, they are not VVic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, they are Friends: Theſe agree with us, with our <hi>Saint</hi> to break Laws; a Tipling Houſe, without Licenſe; yea, a Bawdy Houſe, where there is a Meeting, is like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nay, it is a Meeting Houſe.</p>
            <p>The Quality of the Act was the laſt thing I propounded to ſpeak to, and that appears to be lawful: <hi>It is Lawful for the Saints,</hi> &amp;c. Here you muſt underſtand, that there is a Law written in the Mind, and a Law of the Fleſh written in the Members: Our <hi>Saint</hi> is not guided by the firſt Law, but by the latter, <hi>viz.</hi> The Law of the Fleſh which wars againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104619:9"/>that of the Mind, and by this Law, <hi>It is Lawful for the Saints to Cheat,</hi> &amp;c. Having Explained the Terms, with as much Brevity, as Perſpicuity would admit, and ſhewed you the ſenſe of the VVords in the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt of the Act, and uſe of Cheating. Secondly, who are the VVicked. Thirdly, who are the <hi>Saints</hi> ſpoken of in the Text. I will now ſend out our <hi>Saint</hi> full Cry into the world, with Mouth as wide, as ever any was, at the Bull and Mouth by <hi>Alderſgate</hi>
            </p>
            <q>It is Lawful for the Saints to Cheat the Wicked.</q>
            <p>I my Beloved, it is lawful, full of Law, for the <hi>Saints</hi> to Cheat the VVicked; thoſe ungodly VVretches, thoſe Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, thoſe prophane Sabbath-breakers, thoſe Adulterers, thoſe Enemies, and Perſecutors of the <hi>Saints,</hi> that will not let the <hi>Saints</hi> injoy Liberty of Conſcience; that deny us the comfort of Meeting, Me the comfort of ſpeaking to you, and you the comfort of hearing me; Me the comfort of ſeeing you, and you the comfort of beholding me: Me, ah me! that in the Times of Rebellion, had full liberty, to ſay, and to do, and to teach you to do what we liſted; Me! who had not the Biſhops Lawn-ſleeves, but their Lands. Ah precious Times! VVhen? VVhen, ſhall we ſee thoſe Golden days again?</p>
            <p>In thoſe days I was not accounted a Non-conformiſt, for I did conform to every thing in Faſhion, to every Device the prevailing Party (whereof I was chief) could Invent; Conſcience, then had no check, no tie, all things, were Lawful that were Profitable, and the <hi>Saints</hi> deſires, were their ſureſt Guides.</p>
            <p>Conſcience had got the Head and Maſtery of the Laws, and ſome of you (my Beloved) do remember, that a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might have another mans Eſtate for asking: Ah goodly Times! to be wiſhed, to be hoped for again, but I leave the ſucceſs to your Prayers.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104619:9"/>
            <p>In thoſe days the Text was not in Queſtion, but in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice: No need of a Sermon upon it, the wicked durſt not deny, that the <hi>Saints</hi> might cheat them; their Goods, their Lands, yea, their Lives were at the <hi>Saints</hi> pleaſure, and you know we took them when we pleaſed.</p>
            <p>'Tis unneceſſary to remind you by what means we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this Faculty, otherwiſe you may remember, we did, and accompliſhed all, in the Name of the Lord, we cried out, that Religion was in Danger, and ſet open the Mouths as well of thoſe who underſtood it not, as thoſe who did; not a Kitchin-wench, not a Groom, not a Scullion, but that could Preach, and although they knew nothing elſe, yet could tell in what points true Religion was wronged, and how to mend it.</p>
            <p>VVe Railed againſt the Rulers, and their Government, and Bellowed and roared for Liberty, as Hogs a Killing, and here we brought in conſcience to ſqueak, which ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, that we Murthered Kings and Princes for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake.</p>
            <p>VVe deſtroyed the Government of Church and State, we Kill'd the <hi>Malignants</hi> and took away their Eſtates, and this is the ſum of the <hi>Saints</hi> Priviledge.</p>
            <p>And now my Beloved, is it not Lawful to Cheat them that oppoſe this? yea, it is Lawful; It is profitable, and therefore Lawful.</p>
            <p>And this ſhall be the only Argument I will uſe at preſent to confirm the Text, my own and your Practices ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Illuſtrate the truth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>One word of Application, and I have done.</head>
               <p>Is it Lawful for the <hi>Saints</hi> to Cheat the Wicked? Why this may ſerve for a uſe of Conſolation, it will comfort us in our greateſt Afflictions, let Poverty do its worſt we have a Priviledge, will help us; common Thieves they muſt be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104619:10"/>Hanged, but we have a Priviledge to Cheat. This will fill our Bellies, 'twill fill our Trunks, 'twill aſſiſt our Friends, and make Proviſions for our Poſterity. Ah! what a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing do we injoy! The Wicked in the Text they are kept from it, they muſt not Cheat: They muſt ſtarve rather then uſe this Priviledge they muſt obey the Law, for conſcience-ſake, Conſcience gives us Liberty to Diſobey. They muſt be ſubject to Magiſtrates, our Priviledge exempts us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Is it Lawful for the Saints to cheat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Why then I Exhort you to make uſe of your time, and enjoy this Priviledge, whilſt you live, for you cannot have it in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World: Nay, if the Law or Reaſon prevail, amongſt Law-givers, then the Wings of this Priviledge will be clip'd, therefore uſe it, whilſt you may, whilſt Faction doth laſt, whilſt Sedition is predominant, and brings preferment; That ſo ye may be Furniſhed with the Mammon of Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs which will make Friends for you, when ye fail.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Is it Lawful (my Beloved) for the Saints to cheat the Wicked? Why this may ſerve for Exprobation, how juſtly may we inviegh againſt the wicked in the Text: Thoſe that oppoſe our Right, and deny us this Priviledge, I ſay how juſtly may we inviegh againſt them, as the moſt Ungrateful people in the World! In the late Times of <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> when the Saints Priviledge was Exalted, 'tis well known, that all the wicked had forfeited, all the Rights, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Liberties, Eſtates, and Lives, to us, and yet we, merciful men, ſpared them, we did not take away all, from all: 'Tis true, we Kill'd ſome Thouſands, we Sequeſtred the <hi>Malignants,</hi> we Recovered the Kings and Biſhops Lands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But what is that to the purpoſe? Are not they Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and Kind, who, when they may deſtroy all, ſpare ſome? And did not we ſpare ſome when we had power, and it was lawful for us to Kill all? And yet the wicked are ungrateful, that they have forgot our Kindneſſes, they make no Retaliation, but would if they could take away from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104619:10"/>us even the uſe of <hi>Conventicles.</hi> Ha! my Beloved, what ungodly Wretches are theſe! That would not allow us the Liberty of Meeting. VVhere we have an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, of comforting one another, of eaſing our Minds, and our Bodies, and Refreſhing one another: VVhere we are Fed with the precious Doctine, in the Text, and you hear that, and many other ſuch Truths proceed from my Mouth, as if they were Gods VVord and Divine Revelations. Ha vile! and ungrateful wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked! that would hinder ſuch Mercies, we ſeldom Pray, or Preach, but that we remember them, in our Prayers and Sermons, and yet they return us no thanks, ſo Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful and void of Grace are the wicked!</p>
               <p>And ſince I am fallen upon the Subject of Ingratitude, to ſhew our utter diſlike and abhorency of it, I will Reprove it even in you, even in the Saints, that ſo you may be without ſpot, without blemiſh. You know (my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) that by the Act of Confirmation, of Miniſters, the wicked were Reſtored to their Benefices, and then was I put out of a good Parſonage, and if my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience would have been ſo wicked as to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; yet could I not have gotten a convenient Benefice, ſo contrary was that change to the profit and promotion of the Saints. VVherefore I applied my ſelf to you, and Incited you to the Building of a Meeting Houſe, and the maintaining of a Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Miniſter, who ſhould Inſtruct you, in all the ways of cheating the wicked, and Build you up in Stubbornneſs, and Stiff-neckedneſs, and ſo make you a Choice, Select, peculiar People, to Live and Die in Oppoſition to the Government of Church and State.</p>
               <p>To this you were eaſily perſwaded, and by my pains and the Aſſiſtance, of others, I got to help, of my Cloath, and Coif, you are well grounded in the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104619:11"/>of VVaywardneſs, and throughly Educated, in the Doctrine of the Text. But before I could bring you to a perfect Habit; I and my fellow La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers ſpent many Drops of Sweat, I could not hold out my ſelf, but was forced to ply you with two or three ſtirrers up, one after another, and wirry you, as Dogs the Bear, or Bull ſucceſſively.</p>
               <p>At firſt you conſidered our Extraordinary La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and (to your Praiſe be it ſpoken) you Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed very Bountifully to all our Wants and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities; I my ſelf at one Meeting, have had a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pounds of the Collection, for my own ſhare, and the Sweat of the other Undertakers, have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe been Anſwered by your Drops.</p>
               <p>But now: Ah! It grieves me to tell you of it, I ſpeak it with Tears in my Eyes; you, even you, are very Backward in your Payments and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions. You are grown worſe then any other Conventicle. There is— his Conventicle Raiſes Eighty Pound a time, take one time with another: But many a time, ah! many a time have I ſpent my ſelf upon you, my Bowels have Yerned over you: I ſay many, many a time, and yet I could not raiſe a Heart within you, to make a Purſe of Forty Pounds at moſt, no not Forty Pounds.</p>
               <p>And are not theſe ſad Times? Is not this a ſad Age? When the Saints are ſo ſlow to good Works. Miſtake me not, the ſadneſs doth not ariſe from my Want of that Abundance of Money, your Liberal Contributions, uſed to Supply me with, but from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104619:11"/>this, that your Defect herein, is a Sign you are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from Grace, 'tis a Sign your Zeal is not ſo Warm as it has been, 'tis a Sign the Doctrine we Preach has not ſuch an Influence upon you, as it ought. 'Tis a Sign of a Diſſolution, and that the World will be at an end. Ah! What ſhall I ſay? My Heart is full, my Heart is full. But farewel.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
